Today's דף *daf* is פ"ז *Pezayen*, eighty-seven, and we pick up at
the top of פ"ז עמוד א' *Pezayen Amud Aleph*, but we're going
to just resume from the bottom of פ"ו עמוד ב' *Pevav Amud
Bet* because it's the continuation of pretty much the discussion for half
of the דף *daf*. And we're dealing with the issue that the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has or a משנה mishna *Mishnah* said that if
stuff is left on the fire and it falls off the fire,
stuff that should be burning, before חצות chatzot *Chatzos* it still has
a מצוה *mitzvah* to be burned, there's still מעילה meilah, *Me'ilah*, and
you put it back on the fire; after חצות chatzot, *Chatzos* it
no longer has a מצוה *mitzvah* to be burned, there's no מעילה
meilah *Me'ilah*, and you don't have to put it back on the
fire. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, well what difference does חצות
chatzot *Chatzos* make? Either the stuff has turned to ash or hasn't
turned to ash. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s conclusion, based on a
debate about which פסוק pasuk *pasuk* it's based on, but the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s conclusion is, no, you're right, I mean if it's already
turned to ash then you're done with it even before חצות chatzot
*Chatzos*, and if it's still meat then even after חצות chatzot, *Chatzos*
you put it back. The case in the משנה mishna *Mishnah* where
חצות chatzot. *Chatzos* mattered was a middle case where it was like
hardened; it was as hard as
a rock as it were, but it wasn't yet ash. That case,
before חצות chatzot, *Chatzos* it's still considered the מצוה *mitzvah* to burn
it—we get this from a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*—and there's still מעילה meilah.
*Me'ilah*. After חצות chatzot. *Chatzos* you're done, and there's no מצוה *mitzvah*
to burn it, there's no מעילה me’ilah, *Me'ilah*. So then, and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes—and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to challenge this
in a little bit—that what changes the status of this piece of
meat that's now hard and in this middle state is it's on
the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach* at חצות chatzot *Chatzos*, and then it's considered
the מצוה *mitzvah*'s done. So what happens, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
if the meat is not on the מזבח mizbeach. *mizbe'ach*? It was
up there at 11:50, flew off at 11:50, and now it's 12:10.
Okay, so at this stage the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes you can
put it back because since it wasn't on the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*
at חצות chatzot *Chatzos*, it is not considered to be ash yet,
so you put it back. Now if you actually put it back
on the fire and it burned and it turned to ash, the
story is over. But let's say you didn't get around to putting
it back on the fire, you just put it up at the
top of the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbe'ach*, you haven't put it back on
the fire. Will its status ever change if it missed that first
חצות chatzos *Chatzos*? That's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question. So let's take
a look at that again from the bottom of פ"ו עמוד ב'
*Pevav Amud Bet*. איתמר *Itmar* was said, two lines from the bottom:
פירשו קודם חצות pirshu kodem chatzos, והחזירן אחר חצות chatzos, *Pirshu kodem
Chatzos vehichziran achar Chatzos*. So these pieces of meat came off the
מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach* before חצות chatzos *Chatzos*, were put back after חצות
chatzos *Chatzos*. Okay, so again, if it is put back and put
on the fire and it burns, fine. If it's left at the
base and doesn't put back, presumably when daybreak comes it's נותר notar?
*notar*, so it's no good. But the point was you put it
back up at 12:10 and it didn't—but you didn't burn it yet
and it's not yet ash—when does this ever get to be that
state that it's considered to be done if it missed that first
חצות *Chatzos* which could have changed the state of this piece of
meat? רבה Rabba. אמר חצות שני אוכלתן *Rabbah amar Chatzos sheni ochaltan*.
It is the second חצות *Chatzos*. If it flew off the fire
at 11:50 PM Sunday night and you put it back at
12:10 AM also, whatever, Sunday night, then it only becomes considered the
מצוה *mitzvah*'s done, assuming it doesn't actually turn to ash, at midnight
Monday night. Okay, so every חצות *Chatzos* has that option of turning
something that is in this middle state, considering it to be ash.
Okay, so if it wasn't up there Sunday night midnight, by Monday
night midnight, that's what will happen to it. רב חסדא Rav Chisda
אמר *Rav Chisda amar*, Rav Chisda says, עמוד השחר amud hashachar אוכלתן
*Amud Hashachar ochaltan*. You don't need Monday midnight; Monday
daybreak will make it considered to be no longer fit to be
putting on the מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. Not because by daybreak it's considered
like it's ash and the מצוה *mitzvah*'s done, but by daybreak it's
considered to be נותר notar? *notar*, right? The same way if you
have meat at the bottom that you're eating or meat at the
bottom that you never put on the מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach*, by daybreak
it's נותר notar, *notar*. It's considered to be, you know, once it's
the morning of the next day,
it's leftover and can't be put on the מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. So
this stuff that's sitting at the top of the מזבח mizbei’ach *mizbe'ach*
also, by daybreak it's נותר notar, *notar* and cannot be put back
on the מזבח mizbei’ach, *mizbe'ach*, okay. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda אמר
עמוד השחר amud hashachar, אוכלתן *Rav Chisda amar Amud Hashachar ochaltan*. אמרי
בי רב *Amri bei Rav*, מאי mai טעמא דרב חסדא *mai taimei
de-Rav Chisda*, what's the reasoning of Rav Chisda? ומה חצות שאינו לינה
lina. עושה עיכול *Umah Chatzos she-eino linah oseh ikol*—midnight, that doesn't make
things considered to be slept over; it doesn't make meat that you
have a מצוה *mitzvah* to eat or meat at the bottom of
the מזבח mizbei’ach. *mizbe'ach*, you know, or the entrails, it doesn't make
them considered to be נותר notar *notar*. Midnight has no meaning for
normal things. And nevertheless, midnight has the power to make this meat
considered to be consumed. So עמוד השחר amud hashachar, שעושה לינה lina
*Amud Hashachar she-oseh linah*—daybreak that makes stuff לינה lina *linah*, that basically
takes everything that isn't on the מזבח mizbei’ach. *mizbe'ach*, means it's no
longer fit and so
on—אינו דין שעושה עיכול *eino din she-oseh ikol*, certainly it should make
the stuff at top considered consumed. Okay, so that's Rav Chisda's argument,
which seems to be, if you ignore the קל וחומר *kal vachomer*,
just seems to be a simple point, which is: yes fine, the
stuff is up there on, you know, Sunday night at 12:10; when
Sunday daybreak comes, why doesn't it just become נותר notar? *notar*? And
once it becomes נותר notar *notar*, you shouldn't be allowed to put
it on the fire. Now you could say maybe המזבח מקדש hamizbayach
mekadesh *ha-mizbe'ach mekadesh*, it's נותר notar *notar* but it's at the top
of the מזבח mizbei’ach? *mizbe'ach*, you're allowed to, but still, you know.
The idea that it's considered to be not problematic for רבא Rava
at all after daybreak is a funny idea. We'll see in a
minute why רבא's Rava able to say this. Okay, but anyway, that's
the debate. You need Monday midnight or is it from first thing
Monday morning that the status of this meat changed? So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: פרשו קודם חצות והחזירן לאחר עמוד השחר.
Pirshu kodem chatzot vehachziran le'achar amud hashachar. Let's say it came off
before midnight, 11:50 PM Sunday night, and it stayed at the foot
of the altar until 6:10. We'll assume that עמוד השחר amud hashachar
is 6:00 AM. Actually, 6:00 AM is normally when we assume that
sunrise is, if it's a perfect day, so let's say 5:00 AM
is עמוד השחר, amud hashachar okay? And you returned them to the
altar at, at 5:10 AM. והחזירן לאחר עמוד השחר. vehachziran le'achar amud
hashachar. רבא אמר חצות שני יכול לעשות. Rava amar chatzot sheini yachol
la'asot. רבא Rava says, same thing, it has no change of status,
which is funny. Why doesn't he sort of say that it's נותר?
notar, Okay, so it has no change of status and you have
to wait till Monday midnight.
רב חסדא אמר אין בין איכול לעולם. Rav Chisda amar ein bein
ichul le'olam. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, wait a minute, that
this type of a thing, because it wasn't on the מזבח mizbei’ach?
at עמוד השחר, amud hashachar remember, he was the one that said
עמוד השחר amud hashachar, turns it into consumed, right? That's what רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says. But again, the assumption is, the same way
it needed to be at the top of the altar at חצות
to be considered ashes, so even for רב חסדא Rav Chisda that
says you've got עמוד השחר amud hashachar that turns it into ashes,
that's your backup thing, it has to be at the top of
the altar. If it's at the bottom of the altar, עמוד השחר
amud hashachar didn't turn it into ashes. So according to him, he
would say like, he's consistent with his idea. Like רבא Rava says,
oh, if not this midnight, next midnight. If not that midnight, three
midnights from now, whatever. רב חסדא Rav Chisda, basically says, no, you
don't go looking at other dates. Like since when can you say
that meat put up today, Sunday, you look at Monday's midnight? That's
irrelevant. The only thing that's relevant for Sunday meat is two time
periods: חצות, if it's at the top of the altar, and עמוד
השחר, amud hashachar because עמוד השחר amud hashachar. is always relevant for
things that were brought on Sunday, right? But Monday's חצות is relevant
for Monday's meat, and Monday's עמוד השחר amud hashachar, is relevant for
Monday קרבנות, korbanot, okay? So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, if it
did not have the impact of חצות or עמוד השחר amud hashachar,
when it was at the top of the altar, then its status
never changes. And as long as you want, you can put it
back on the fire. Now, all of that is very nice, except
why didn't it become נותר? notar Right, that's not explained, right? So
if it was at the foot of the altar, why—and the answer
might be, you know what, maybe it did become נותר, nosar but
you went ahead, you didn't ask any questions, you put it at
the top of the altar. So now it's the הלכה halacha that
מזבח מקדש. mizbe'ach mekadesh. It was נותר, nosar. it was put at
the top of the altar, it gets to stay there and it
can be put on the fire. The only thing that you don't
have to put on the fire is something that is considered already
ashes. So the fact that it's נותר nosar? isn't enough, okay? So
you get—like, what's your question?
So my question is, I mean, I'm just trying to, you know,
this is all very nice, I'm just thinking this is getting too
abstract in so far as I would figure that there's just so
much going on on top of the מזבח. Mizbayach You're really going
to know this piece versus that piece versus the other piece? I
was thinking that too.
How would they know? No, no, I'm being really serious.
You know, Michael, I have no idea.
Is there any way to know?
Yeah, you can label them. Exactly, they give them numbers, like
pieces in the IKEA.
So here's your fire, right?
Here's your piece of meat. So if—and here, here's חצות,
okay? Here's חצות.
You have to make one of those Magritte pictures, you know, like...
yeah, yeah,
okay, here's עמוד השחר. amud hashachar Very famous picture.
Yeah, the one about Napoleon's trips or whatever?
No, no, the one where like it's dark and there, you know,
streetlights are on, but then like right on top it's like the
sky.
Anyway, okay. So here's this meat. If it's up there, so it's
not—it's hard, but it's not ashes. If while it's on the מזבח
Mizbayach, it passes חצות, then at this stage it's considered to be,
right? You know, I need a different color, whatever. Anyway, if it
passes here, then at this stage it's considered to be ashes.
Assuming it's really actually turned into ashes, right?
No, no. If it's actually turned into ashes, you don't need any
of this, okay? You only need this, you only need this if
it's hardened. If it's actually ashes, then there's no מצווה mitzvah even
before חצות. And if it's actually still good juicy meat, then even
after חצות there's a מצווה mitzvah to return it. It's only by
the hardened type, okay? So anyway, so you hear it here, okay?
If it's here, חצות passes. If it comes down and goes back
up, okay, and then it's here at עמוד השחר, amud hashachar so
according to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda when it's back on עמוד השחר,
amud hashachar. so that makes it considered to be ashes, okay? This
is all like, you know, this is all let's say, here's Sunday
day and then this is Sunday
night. Okay, then if it remains down
here... So
if it remains, so רבא Rava says no, it's not עלות השחר,
Alot Hashachar, it needs to pass into Monday midnight in order to
be considered to be ashes. Okay, but let's say it comes down
here, okay, that's if it came down and came back up here.
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda would say as soon as עלות השחר
Alot Hashachar it's considered to be ashes, and that all assumes that
that change of status has to happen at the top of the
מזבח. Mizbayach Okay, and רבא Rava says it has to be midnight.
And in the case where it came down and went up here,
so רבא Rava, would still say, okay, by Monday midnight its status
changes. And רב חסדא Rav Chisda would say, no, you only get
for Sunday meat these, you know,
maybe midnight but I disagree with רבא, Rava, so עלות השחר, Alot
Hashachar, okay, I mean no, I don't disagree, רבא, Rava I'm sorry,
you only get midnight and it missed midnight, so you only get
עלות השחר. Alot Hashachar. Once you're into Monday no other time matters.
Now what about the fact that it was down here and it
became עלות השחר Alot Hashachar and it was נותר? nosar Okay, it
was נותר nosar but it was put back up here, so it
gets to stay up. So the only thing that would prevent it
from being put on the fire is if it's considered ashes. And
for רבא Rava it could still be considered ashes when you hit
Monday midnight. But for רב חסדא Rav Chisda if you miss the
Sunday dates it never gets considered to be ashes and you can
always put it... once it's back up here, down here it's נותר
nosar? but once you got it back up here... It could stay
down there for three days? What? Yeah, I mean again what happens
if it's complete, I mean it's already inedible but it's not ashes
yet. So you put it back up here, you know, and you're
totally fine. Maybe who knows, maybe it's not even נותר, nosar it's
an interesting question. If it's completely inedible when עלות השחר Alot Hashachar
hits, I don't even know if it would have a status of
נותר nosar? because it's no longer meat, but it's not yet ashes.
Okay, so anyway but either way you put it back up here,
it wasn't yet ashes because it wasn't on the מזבח Mizbayach when
either of these two critical times existed. So for רב חסדא Rav
Chisda it never becomes considered ashes, it's not yet ashes and you
can always put it back on the fire.
So what time did the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash open?
עלות השחר. Alot Hashachar.
Right, so it means putting it like... and it closed?
No, the כהנים Kohanim were there all night. Oh they were. Yeah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, מתקיף לה רב
יוסף, matkif lah Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked, מאן
לימא לן דחצות בראש המזבח משוי ליה עיכול? man leima lan dechatzos
beroash hamizbeach mashvei lei ikul? Now both רבא Rava and רב חסדא
Rav Chisda assume that midnight changes its status only if it's at
the top of the altar. But who told you that that was
correct? Maybe wherever the meat is, it's considered to be ashes once
midnight hits, you know, and once it's basically hardened. דילמא כל היכא
דמשתכח משוי ליה עיכול? deilma kol heicha d'mishtachach mashvei lei ikul?
Maybe wherever it is, the midnight considers it turns it into ashes.
Okay, so that's good question. Your whole debate, which is a fascinating
debate, assumes that the status change only happens once it's on the
altar. If the meat is at the floor its status change doesn't
happen. But who says that's true?
So שלחו מתם, shalchu mitem, they sent from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
הלכתא כרב יוסף, hilchesa keRav Yosef, you know what רב יוסף Rav
Yosef is correct, its status change occurs wherever it is. So you
don't have your fun little debate because wherever it is, you know,
unless it goes into a time warp and it completely lives in
a space where there's no midnight, I don't know, if it goes
up in an Einsteinian ship and goes faster than the speed of
light, actually that means it'll come down and it'll still be before
midnight. Okay, so anyway forget that. Anyway, so he says wherever midnight
is it's going to change its status. Now תוספות Tosafos has an
interesting point. They sent from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the הלכה Halacha
is like רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So if you look at תוספות,
Tosafos, הלכתא כרב יוסף, hilchesa keRav Yosef, פירוש יפה אמר, perush yafeh
amar, it means yeah what רב יוסף Rav Yosef says is very
persuasive logically. ואין זה פסק הלכה, ve'ein zeh psak Halacha, we're not
really פסקנינג paskening הלכה למעשה Halacha l'maaseh because it's קרבנות. Korbanos. ולא
שייך למיפך הלכתא למשיחא? velo shayach lemeifach hilchesa lemishicha?
So why didn't the גמרא Gemara ask like it does sometimes, right,
what, you're פסקנינג paskening for something that'll be relevant at the time
of משיח? Moshiach? אלא בסוף נמי מוכח דלא פליגי עליה. ela besof
nami mochi d'lo paligi alei. Anyway
תוספות Tosafos says no you're going to see the גמרא Gemara is
going to reinterpret what they were saying. Anyway, so that's cute, right?
It is funny, they sent from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you should
know the הלכה Halacha is like רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Anyway, fine.
But what רב יוסף Rav Yosef says makes sense, its status should
change wherever it is. Okay,
איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was also taught, אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, פירשו קודם חצות, if it fell
off the מזבח Mizbayach before midnight, והחזירון אחר חצות, vehechzirun achar chatzos,
and you returned it after, לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo
moalin. There's no מעילה, Meilah that midnight was effective to make it
no מעילה Meilah even though it wasn't on the מזבח Mizbayach at
midnight. וכן תנא בר קפרא, vechen tana Bar Kappara, בר קפרא Bar
Kappara taught the same thing: פירשו קודם חצות והחזירון אחר חצות יוצאין
מידי מעילה. pirshu kodem chatzos vehechzirun achar chatzos yotzin midei meilah. If
it was off and it was not put on until after חצות
you still there's still no מעילה. Meilah. Okay, and again presumably that
also means no מצווה mitzvah to put it back on, you're done.
Okay, so you see everybody says that even if it's not on
the מזבח Mizbayach at חצות, חצות has the effect wherever it is.
So אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amlei Rav Papa l'Abaye, רב פפא
Rav Papa said to אביי: Abaye: וכי מאחר דשלחו מתם vechi me'achar
deshalchu mitem הלכתא כרב יוסף, hilchesa keRav Yosef, since they sent from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that the הלכה Halacha is like רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא, ve'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba,
and רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba says it, וכן
תנא בר קפרא, vechen tana Bar Kappara, and בר קפרא Bar Kappara
has a ברייתא Baraisa that says it, רבא ורב חסדא במאי פליגי?
Rava veRav Chisda bemai paligi? What is their debate? It's a great
fascinating debate, but what's the circumstances of it? רבא Rava ורב חסדא
Rav Chisda במאי פליגי? b’mai pligi? What is their debate? It’s a
great fascinating debate, but what’s the circumstances of it, if חצות always
has an effect wherever something is? So אמר ליה amar lei בשמנים.
b’shmanim. He says to him, in fatty meat. Now what the heck
does this mean? I gotta tell you, I didn’t understand it. Rashi,
if you look at Rashi, Rashi says, Rashi says בשמנים, b’shmanim, Rashi
says about ten lines down on the narrow lines, אפילו הוקשו לא
הוי עיכול דשומנא מעכבן מלעשות דשן. Afilu hukshu lo havei ichul d’shumna
m’akvan mei’la’asos deshen. Even if they’re hardened, because they’re fatty, okay, they’re
not yet, they’re not considered to be consumed, because I don’t know,
eventually they dry out. Maybe it means it’s dry on the outside
but it’s still some moisture on the inside. Okay, so it’s even
a, it’s even a less middle case. It’s a case where it’s
still inclining a little bit to be closer to real meat. So
what’s the point? So like once your argument is this הלכה halakha
of midnight doesn’t matter where the meat is, now we have three
categories. If it’s, if it’s really meat, then even after midnight it
still is מעילה, Meilah it still goes back. If it’s ashes, even
before midnight. If it’s hardened, so then when it hits to be
midnight, whether it’s at the top of the מזבח Mizbayach or whether
it’s at the bottom of the מזבח, Mizbayach? once it’s midnight it’s
considered ashes. If it’s hardened but fatty, then it needs to be
both midnight and at the top of the מזבח. Mizbayach Like what
sense does that make? I can understand that there’s another category, like
hard on the outside but still a little moisture on the inside,
but what I can’t understand is like make up your mind. Either
midnight changes the status wherever it is or it changes the status
only if it’s at the top of the מזבח. Mizbayach Why should,
what’s the, what’s the logic of this combination, that if it’s not
totally hardened, midnight will have the effect but only if it’s also
at the top of the מזבח? Mizbayach I don’t really understand it.
But anyway, by creating this other new category, we’re allowed to say
that this debate of רבא Rava and רב חסדא Rav Chisda still
exists in the special circumstances of fatty meat. Okay. Yeah, what does
your note say?
Read the little note here. The answer is that we are dealing
with meats that are fatty at the first midnight but dried out
after being returned to the pyre. Rava and Rav Chisda disagree whether
they are considered consumed at dawn or at the following midnight.
So they’re fatty when they at the first midnight.
Yeah. Oh, so at this oh, I see. So at this midnight,
midnight didn’t change their status because they weren’t yet hardened, but they
were dried out after being returned to the pyre. Oh, okay, now
I understand it. Thank you. That’s a helpful explanation. I wish Rashi
had said that. Okay. Who does he quote?
שפת אמת. Sfas Emes. שפת אמת. Sfas Emes.
חזון איש. Chazon Ish. Oh, okay, that’s a much better explanation. You
understand that explanation? So what it means is it didn’t, it didn’t
have to say fatty meat, it could have just said meat that
was not yet dried out, so therefore midnight didn’t have the effect,
it wasn’t dried out. And then you put it back and you
want to know if it gets dried out by over the course
of the night, is there another point that it’ll be considered. Oh,
okay, that’s an excellent explanation. Okay. So what it basically means is
it’s meat that was still in the meat state at the first
midnight and then it got put back at the altar and you
wanted to know if it gets dried out by, oh, excellent. Okay,
for once I’m very happy that you read the
note. But anyway, okay, that’s very good. So that’s the point. The
first midnight didn’t have its effect. But now by the time you
get to עמוד השחר amud hashachar or the second midnight, it is
dried out and we do want to know is there another time
after the first midnight? ורב חסדא v’Rav Chisda says עמוד השחר amud
hashachar, is the time, and if it was at the bottom and,
no, well you don’t have the second part, oh yeah I guess
the second part of the debate is, it remains meat, it remains
meaty even through עמוד השחר. amud hashachar So right, so rather than
being at the bottom, the scenario of their debate is it remained
meaty when these times were passing. So רב חסדא will say if
you miss the first time and it was meaty and it’s dry
by עמוד השחר fine, but that has the effect, but if it
remained meaty that entire period, then there’s no other time period that
turns it into ashes. ורבא v’Rava always says you don’t go by
עמוד השחר, you go by the following night’s midnight. So you’ll always
have the next midnight. Okay, nice explanation. Yeah.
Question about that הלכה. halakha. So is it impossible that you know
maybe in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the place where there was a
מקדש Mikdash there might have been a מסורה mesorah on this kind
of
a issue and why do they say הלכה halakha meaning like that
we actually know that that’s the in this kind of I doubt
it, I doubt it. And הלכה halakha is rarely because there was
already the a practice, הלכה halakha is usually a פסק. psak. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, where were we?
בעי מיניה רבא מרבה. ba’ei minei Rava mei’Rabba. רבא Rava asked
רבה. Rabbah לינה מועלת בראשו של מזבח או אינה מועלת בראשו של
מזבח? Lina mo’eles b’rosho shel mizbei’ach o einah mo’eles b’rosho shel mizbei’ach?
If something actually, forget this whole thing about dried out, ashes, the
whole thing. I’ve got some meat of my חטאת. chatas. I’m a
כהן. kohen. And it is, we’re going to say עמוד השחר is
5:00 AM, and it’s 4:30 in the morning. And we know it’s
all going to turn
into into into נותר nosar in a half hour. I don’t want
to give it up, it’s some nice piece of steak.
But it’s on the מזבח?
mizbeach No it’s on me down here I’m eating, wait, I’m giving
you my scenario. I'm eating it yet, but oh my gosh, half
hour, it's going to be נותר. nosar I don't want to give
up this nice steak. So can I just go ahead and put
it on the מזבח mizbeach. and then when morning hits, okay? It
after morning hits, whatever, I'll take it back down or whatever, you
know, does that prevent it from becoming נותר? nosar. Or in a
case where we're not talking about eating the meat, let's say we're
talking about, you know, putting the stuff on the altar, it's the
meat of an עולה olah or of a whatever, okay, if it's
on the מזבח, mizbeach, well that actually would be less relevant because
the מזבח mizbeach. is מקדש. mekadesh. So let's see the case. Okay,
לינת ראש המזבח אין לינת ראש המזבח? linat rosh hamizbayach ein linat
rosh hamizbayach? היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא דלא ירדו,
ilima d'lo yardu, which is what the גמרא Gemara says, השתא לנו
בעזרה אמרת דלא ירדו בראש המזבח מיבעיא? hashta lanu b'azara amrat d'lo
yerdu b'rosh hamizbayach mibaya?
If the stuff is still up on the altar, let's not take
my case of eating the steak, let's take case of meat of
an עולה. olah. If the meat of the עולה olah is still
up on the altar, so even if it's considered נותר nosar by
daybreak, okay, who cares if it's נותר nosar when it's on the
top of the altar? Okay, the question is does the top of
the altar prevent it from becoming נותר? nosar But if it's on
the altar at daybreak, so then it gets just stay on the
altar, right? Even if it was נותר nosar because it was at
the floor and was put at the altar. So ואלא דירדו. ve'ella
deyardu. Okay, so here's the question. The question is, so let's not
deal with my case of, although you could I guess eating the
meat, but let's for a minute assume we're dealing with the meat
of the עולה. olah. Okay, it was up on the altar when
it was daybreak, and then you took it down. Can you now
say since it was on the altar at daybreak it never became
נותר? nosar And now I'll be allowed to put it back up
and to allow it to burn. Got it? Since it was on
the altar, is that part of like המזבח מקדש Mikdash or more
than that like does it sort of take it out of the
zone, you know, somehow, of being in the עזרה, azara, and therefore
the נותר nosar. doesn't apply to it? And since it was not
נותר nosar. when I brought it down, I'll be able to now
put it back up because it never became נותר. nosar, Okay.
Meaning I'm, meaning the next day and then it fell down?
Yeah, yeah, it was up at the top of the altar, it
was the next day and it fell off the top of the
altar. Do I get to put it back up and to burn
it now?
Why do we think you couldn't?
Because it became נותר notar, as of when it fell
off like so what?
ירדו לא יעלו. yardu lo ya'alu. Even when stuff was on the
מזבח mizbeach. and it comes down you can't put it back up
if it's פסול. pasul. So is it, if it's נותר notar and
it falls off... Michael, if I had a piece that was actually
נותר notar? and I put it up, okay, I would be allowed
to then burn it, but if it fell off I wouldn't be
allowed to put it back up, right?
If it fell off before the time, but meaning but now it's
like in other words as long as it's on the מזבח mizbeach
it's not like there's no time's up on it.
That's the question. You're assuming לינה אינה מועלת, lina eina moelet, but
the גמרא Gemara is not so sure. Okay. ואלא לשולחן מדמינן לה?
ve'ella leshulchan medaminan lah? Is it like לשולחן? leshulchan? And we're going
to have a הלכה halacha that when bread is on the שולחן,
shulchan, the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, it doesn't... No, but besides שבת,
Shabbos, because that you could say is its normal זמן, zman, the
fact that it's supposed to be there the whole week. So that's
not a proof that it doesn't become לינה. lina, That's like saying
שלמים shelamim doesn't become לינה lina, because of the first morning. It's
not yet the time is up. But there's a הלכה halacha that
even when it's been more than the time, it doesn't become נותר
notar on the שולחן. shulchan. What's the
הלכה? halacha? דתנן, ditnan, אפילו הן על שולחן ימים רבים אין בכך
כלום. afilu hen al shulchan yamim rabim ein bekach klum. Even if
they're for many days. What's the scenario? The רש"י Rashi says the
scenario is that the כהנים kohanim for some reason didn't get around
to putting up the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim on שבת. Shabbos. That's
when you put it up, on שבת. Shabbos. They only put it
up on Sunday. So when do you offer, when do you eat
the לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? When do you offer up the בזיכין?
bazichin? So you can't say you offer it up next שבת Shabbos
because it's only been on six days. So the time to be
מקריב makriv the בזיכין bazichin hasn't arrived yet. It's מחוסר זמן. mechusar
zman. It has to be on the שולחן shulchan for a week,
that's the assumption. So therefore what you do is you skip a
שבת Shabbos offering it, and you offer the בזיכין bazichin and you
eat the bread another next שבת. Shabbos. So it's been on the
שולחן shulchan for thirteen days, okay, so that's clearly longer than the
week, but it doesn't become נותר notar, once it's on the שולחן.
shulchan.
But wait, how do you know it's supposed to be on there
six days as opposed to just till שבת? Shabbos? Let's say you
forget you just wait till שבת?
Shabbos? Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara assumes, though, okay, it's not
our סוגיא sugya right now, but it assumes that's considered מחוסר זמן,
mechusar zman, that it's not just a הלכה halacha that you offer
it on שבת, Shabbos, it's a הלכה halacha that it has to
be there for seven days. Okay, and therefore the משנה Mishna. says
that it's not נותר. notar Okay. או דילמא לקרקע מדמינן לה? o
dilma lekarka medaminan lah? Or do we say it's like the floor?
So רש"י Rashi says to some degree the question is to what
degree is the מזבח mizbeach a כלי, kli, or to what degree
is the מזבח mizbeach like a vessel, to what degree is the
מזבח mizbeach, just like the architecture, just like, you know, actually connected
to the ground of the מקדש mekadesh, and therefore it's like it's
on the floor. And that's why it's in this middle state. Because
the presumption is if it's in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, that
saves it from נותר. notar? If it's on the floor it doesn't.
What if it's on the מזבח? mizbeach So אמר ליה, amar lei,
he said back to him, אין לינה בראש המזבח. ein lina b'rosh
hamizbayach. At the top of the מזבח mizbeach. it does not become
נותר, notar so even if it falls off after you can put
it back up. Like I said, I realized when I was giving
my example of eating my steak, I'm not sure that would be
the same, because maybe this is the question. Remember, the מזבח mizbeach
is only מקדש את הראוי לו. mekadesh es harauy lo. The גמרא
Gemara didn't use the phrase here of מזבח מקדש, Mizbayach mekadesh, it
used the phrase לינה אינה מועלת, lina eina moelet, right? So I
don't know if it's the same exact concept. But meat of קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodashim, which doesn't have the הלכה halacha that the מזבח
mizbeach somehow is מקדש, mekadesh. right, like you know for the earlier
הלכות, halachos, right, if it's the meat of קדשי קדשים... kodshei kodashim...
So presumably the same would be true for this לינה lina question.
Presumably this לינה, lina the fact that the מזבח mizbeach saves it
from לינה, lina. presumably is about stuff that belongs on the מזבח.
mizbeach Presumably would not help for the meat of קרבנות korbanot that
you're supposed to be eating. Okay, so that's just, my
example might not have been a good example, but it's an interesting
question. Would this apply also to meat that you're supposed to be
eating? Okay, now גמרא Gemara continues. By the way, here's another type
of רבה Rabbah and רב חסדא question. So you kept it on
the מזבח, mizbeach it didn't become נותר, notar fell off, okay, it's
not נותר notar, yet even though it's after daybreak. Does the next
daybreak make it into נותר?
notar, Meaning if you just left it there for yet another day?
Yeah, it fell off Sunday morning after daybreak, okay, now it's Monday
morning after daybreak. Does it become נותר Nosar now? Think so. So
anyway, interesting question. Okay, anyway, now קבלה מיניה או לא. kibla minei
o lo. So did he accept this answer or not, that the,
you know, the decision, you know, he sort of said, it seems
to me that לינה Linah does not have an effect when it's
on the מזבח. Mizbeach תא שמע דאיתמר Ta shema de-itamar was taught.
אברים שלנו בעזרה. Evarim she-lanu ba-azarah. If you have the limbs of
a קרבן korban that were left in the עזרה, azarah, מקטיר והולך
כל הלילה. makater ve-holech kol ha-laylah. So you can offer it up
the whole night. לן בראש שעל מזבח. Lan be-rosh she-al mizbeach.
Let's say you actually kept the limbs at the top of the
altar and presumably then they fell down, because if they're still up
then obviously the הלכה halacha is לא ירדו. lo yerdu. מקטיר והולך
לעולם. Makater ve-holech le-olam.
I'm sorry, I keep on jumping ahead of myself. Okay, I'm sorry.
לן בראש שעל מזבח Lan be-rosh she-al mizbeach and they're still there,
מקטיר והולך לעולם. makater ve-holech le-olam. So if they're still at the
top of the altar, מזבח מקדש, mizbeach mekadesh, and obviously you could
keep them up on the altar and burn them whenever you want.
ירדו, Yerdu, if they came down.
Meaning you didn't put it on the fire but they're just on
the.
Exactly. ירדו, Yerdu, which is exactly our case, so they were on
the altar when daybreak occurred and now they're on the bottom. This
was exactly our case, because as long as they're still there, מזבח
מקדש mizbeach mekadesh and you get to keep it up. רבה אמר
יעלו. Rabbah amar ya'alu. רבה Rabbah says, okay, it doesn't become נותר,
Nosar. you can put it back up. רבא אמר לא יעלו. Rava
amar lo ya'alu. And רבא Rava, says, no, you can't. So רבה
Rabbah had his position that לינה Linah. is not מועלת moelet בראש
שעל מזבח. be-rosh she-al mizbeach. It doesn't become לינה. linah. And רבא,
Rava sorry Michael because it even looks like רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens
like רבא Rava against your intuition. רבא Rava says actually no, it
does become נותר Nosar even at the top of the מזבח. Mizbeach
שמע מינה לא קבלה מיניה. Shema mina lo kibla minei. You see
רבא Rava did not accept רבה'ס Rabbah's position, because here רבא Rava.
and רבה Rabbah debate. שמע מינה, Shema mina, that's a good point.
So here's the question, the meat when it's at the מזבח Mizbeach
at daybreak. So we know מזבח Mizbeach. is מקדש פסולים, mekadesh pesulim,
but does מזבח Mizbeach keep it in enough of a separate zone
to say that it does not become נותר? nosar, And that's a
debate of רבה Rabbah and רבא. Rava Like I said, you could
ask maybe everybody might agree in a case of it's meat that's
to be eaten. Okay, who knows? But anyway, we're talking about meat
of an עולה, olah, that's where it belongs on the מזבח, Mizbeach
we would say מזבח מקדש. mizbeach mekadesh. So רבה Rabbah says the
מזבח Mizbeach prevents it from becoming נותר nosar. even if it fell
out off you could put it back up. And רבא Ravva, says
no, it still becomes נותר nosar. at the top of the
מזבח. Mizbeach רבה Rabbah, was אביי Abaye and רבא'ס Rava's רבי. rebbe.
Yeah, so he's disagreeing with his רבי? rebbe?
Yeah, you're allowed to. So if it stays at the top of
the מזבח Mizbeach you are, according to רבה, Rabbah, but if it
stays at the top of the מזבח Mizbeach. everybody agrees you can
put it on, because then מזבח מקדש mizbeach mekadesh once it's there
even if it's פסול pasul it gets to stay on. Okay, now
כשם שהמזבח מקדש. keshem she-ha-mizbeach mekadesh. Now we switch gears, that this
הלכה halacha does not only apply to the altar, but it also
applies to the ramp, okay, that the ramp also, you know, makes
stuff that's פסול pasul okay. And we're going to also see, and
the משנה Mishna. also says it applies
to the כלים kelim
and to the כלי שרת. klei shares. And we actually saw that
just a minute ago, or at least a version of that by
the שלחן, shulchan, that the שלחן shulchan actually if it's a כלי
kli it actually was that way. And at least the way we
just discussed נותר, nosar a כלי kli was more powerful, right? Being
on the שלחן shulchan prevented something from becoming נותר, nosar being on
the מזבח mizbe'ach does not. Okay, so anyway, now we're going to,
so let's take a look, extending this from the מזבח mizbe'ach, to
the ramp and to the כלים. kelim. So תנו רבנן, tano rabbanan,
our rabbis taught. הנוגע במזבח כל הנוגע במזבח יקדש. Ha-nogea ba-mizbeach, kol
ha-nogea ba-mizbeach yikdash. איני אלא מזבח, Eni ela mizbeach,
I only know if it touches the altar. כבש מניין, Kevesh minayin,
how do I know the ramp? תלמוד לומר את המזבח. Talmud lomar
et ha-mizbeach. Now that פסוק pasuk את המזבח et ha-mizbeach is not
in the
verse כל הנוגע במזבח יקדש. kol ha-nogea ba-mizbeach yikdash. There's a major
מחלוקת machlokes which פסוק pasuk את המזבח et ha-mizbeach is referring to.
Okay, רש"י Rashi says it's a פסוק pasuk that basically says when
it speaks about anointing it. It says, what's the פסוק pasuk רש"י
Rashi quotes? רש"י Rashi quotes, yeah, verse 37. ומשחת את
המזבח.
Mashachta et
ha-mizbeach.
So it's about the anointing. The anointing causes it to be sanctified.
Okay,
כלי שרת מניין, klei shares minayin, how do you know the כלי
שרת klei shares become sanctified and have this power? So this actually
is a מפורש פסוק. meforash pasuk. תלמוד לומר כל הנוגע בהם יקדש.
Talmud lomar kol ha-nogea ba-hem yikdash. The פסוק pasuk actually
says ומשחת אותם, umashachta otam, כל הנוגע בהם. kol ha-nogea ba-hem. So
the פסוק pasuk. that actually talks about anointing explicitly is talking about
the כלי שרת, klei shares, and the same way it says כל
הנוגע במזבח יקדש, kol ha-nogea ba-mizbeach yikdash, it says it about the
כלי שרת. klei sharet. So it's actually pretty explicit that the כלי
שרת klei sharet are מקדש. mekadesh Okay, now what does מקדש mekadesh
mean? Right, by the מזבח mizbe'ach it מקדש Mekadesh meant because we
learned it from the פסוק pasuk by the beginning of צו, Tzav,
היא העלה על מוקדה על המזבח. hi ha-olah al mokdah al ha-mizbeach.
that if something is up there it gets to stay up there.
What does מזבח mizbe'ach. what does כלי שרת מקדש kli shares mekadesh.
mean? If something's in a כלי שרת Klei Shares and it's פסול
Pasul what's exactly the הלכה Halacha like? Right, it's one thing to
say if it's on the מזבח mizbe'ach it gets to stay there
and you can just move it to the fire. Let's say I
put my I don't know my טמא Tamei meat in a כלי
שרת. Kli Shares Can I now put it on the fire? Like
conceptually even if you say it's the same מקדש Mekadesh it's a
little different because by putting it on the fire you're like changing
its space, right? Okay, so now it says like this, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. So בעי מיניה ריש לקיש מרבי
יוחנן. Ba'i Minei Reish Lakish Merabi Yochanan. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
asked רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. כל
כלי שרת מהו שיקדש את הפסולין. Kol Klei Shares Mahu Sheyekadesh Es
Hapsulin. So does כלי שרת Kli Shares. sanctify things that are invalid?
Right? I mean that seems to be the case of the משנה.
mishnah אמר ליה תניתוה. Amar Lei Tanituha. What do you mean does
it sanctify invalid things? It's our
משנה. mishna, כשם שהמזבח והכבש מקדשין את הראוי להן כך כלים מקדשין.
Keshem Shehamizbeach Vehakevesh Mekadshin Es Haraui Lahen Kach Kelim Mekadshin. So כלים
Kelim sanctify. So what's exactly the scenario that a כלי שרת Klei
Shares is מקדש? Mekadesh? We just had an example before by לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim that it doesn't become נותר nosar, but what would
be another scenario? Okay, so אמר ליה לכתחילה ליקרב קמיבעיא לי. Amar
Lei Lechatchila Likarev Kamibaia Li. No no no, here's my question. My
question is
you've got this דם Dam let's say that you caught in a
כלי שרת, Kli Shares okay? And then the דם Dam becomes נותר.
I don't know maybe it doesn't become נותר based on what we
just said but the דם Dam becomes טמא Tamei let's say. Okay,
and now if I if you tell me when meat becomes פסול
Pasul and it's on the מזבח mizbe'ach, I can go ahead and
push it on the fire, right? Put it on the fire. If
דם Dam becomes פסול Pasul and it's in the כלי שרת Kli
Shares, maybe I should לכתחילה Lechatchila be allowed to put it on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. What else would מזבח מקדש mizbe'ach mekadesh. mean? I
mean כלי שרת מקדש. kli shares mekadesh מקדש Mekadesh means if מקדש
Mekadesh. at the top of the altar means you get to keep
it on the altar and even move it to the fire. Now
obviously there's a difference. The difference is when you take it from
the כלי שרת Kli Shares to the מזבח mizbe'ach. you're dislocating it,
right? But what else but what else is would be the meaning
of it being מקדש? Mekadesh It means that it allows you to
ignore the פסול. Psul. So what exactly does it mean to allow
you to ignore the פסול? Psul? That you go forward, okay? So
is that what we're saying?
So לכתחילה ליקרב קמיבעיא לי. Lechatchila Likarev Kamibaia Li. So רש"י Rashi
says what is the alternative of כלי שרת Kli Shares מקדש Mekadesh
could mean if it would not mean to be put on the
altar? So any thoughts? Let's see if you can if you can
figure out what רש"י. Rashi. He goes like yeah, I mean obviously
if it's and but the analogy to the מזבח mizbe'ach, would mean
if you're allowed to burn it at the top of the מזבח
mizbe'ach if it's on the altar keep it there, if כלי שרת
Kli Shares you're allowed to put it. But let's say no כלי
שרת Kli Shares is only מקדש Mekadesh? in its space but once
you remove it you're going to change it, it won't. So so
what what meaning does it have to be מקדש?
Mekadesh It means that you don't have to like get rid of
it right away as long as it's in the כלי שרת. Kli
Shares In other words it doesn't become like you know לינה linah
right away.
Well that could be like we said before about the about the
שולחן, Shulchan, maybe it prevents לינה. linah. But רש"י Rashi says no
here's the הלכה Halacha you never would have thought of it if
you're not because of the mode we're thinking of. רש"י Rashi says
the הלכה Halacha is that certain things there's only מעילה Meilah once
you put them in a כלי שרת. Kli Shares Okay, so therefore
like if let's say I make a מנחה Mincha at home and
I do the flour and whatever and even if I verbally sanctify
it, okay, there's no מעילה Meilah until it gets into a כלי
שרת. Kli Shares. So let's say it's פסול Pasul and then it
gets into a כלי שרת Kli Shares. that still has the power
of making it now fit for being מעילה. meila So actually it's
not like a good thing, you know normally we've been saying מקדש
Mekadesh in a way that actually means it makes it okay even
though it was פסול Pasul and allows it to be brought. So
רש"י Rashi says maybe not, maybe by the כלי שרת Kli Shares.
it just means that it literally sanctifies it, meaning before we've been
using the word מקדש Mekadesh? to mean essentially allow me to gloss
over a problem. But literally מקדש Mekadesh means sanctify so maybe it
just means it raises its sanctity and makes it now that it's
in a category of מעילה but maybe it doesn't make it fit
to be brought as a קרבן. Korban. That's only a הלכה Halacha
for the מזבח mizbe'ach, and it's already on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, So
that's the question that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is asking רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. Okay yeah.
If the substance is טמא Tamei it wouldn't make the כלי שרת
Kli Shares טמא? Tamei?
I'm sorry
one more time.
Yeah so say the blood. No. The כלי שרת Klei Shares changes
that and affects the כלי שרת.
Kli Shares No it would affect the כלי שרת? Kli Shares I
mean it depends the level of טומאה. Tumah.
No normal טומאה Tumah would only apply a כלי Kli could only
become טמא Tamei in contact with an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah not
with not with food which would already be a ראשון. Rishon. But
I just have to modify my... what?
Blood would be an אב הטומאה. Av Hatumah.
No not unless it's like the blood of a זב Zav or
something. No.
I'm sorry I misread רש"י. Rashi. I said that the נפקא מינה
Nafka Mina was מעילה but actually I reread רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says actually he gives another a different נפקא מינה. Nafka Mina. I
don't know what רש"י Rashi would say about the מעילה question. But
רש"י Rashi says the נפקא מינה Nafka Mina would be whether you
could be פודה Podeh redeem it. Once something is sanctified in a
כלי שרת Kli Shares. it can't have פדיון Pidyon you can't be
פודה. Podeh. Okay so if something if my מנחה Mincha became טמא
Tamei before I put it in a כלי שרת Kli Shares? I'll
just redeem it and go ahead and use the money and buy
another מנחה. Mincha. But if it became טמא Tamei and then I
put it in a כלי שרת Kli Shares okay once it's put
or you know or even if it wasn't טמא Tamei Okay, before
it was in a כלי שרת Kli Shares I could redeem it,
once it's in a כלי שרת Kli Shares I can't redeem it.
Okay, so רש״י Rashi says that's the הלכה halacha כלי שרת kli
shares מקדש. Mekadesh Literally, you put it in a כלי שרת kli
shares and it raises the sanctity, it can't be redeemed, okay, and
maybe that's all it means and maybe it doesn't mean anything about
this question about making a פסול pasul fit to be offered. So
that was ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's question.
Is it still אי לאו אסיפא ee lav asseifa what you were
saying?
I have to check the מעילה נפקא מינה, nafka mina, so hold
off on that, okay, I don't want to misspeak, but I just
reread רש״י Rashi and רש״י Rashi was talking about the פדיון pidyon
issue, okay. So anyway, but he says, but the question about about
ignoring a פסול, pasul, he says first of all, partly we get
that not just from the fact that the תורה Torah says קדוש,
kadosh, right? I mean again, it's funny, our משנה speaks about מזבח
מקדש. mizbe'ach mekadesh But the idea that you can be okay with
a פסול pasul at the top of the מזבח mizbe'ach, is learned
from a different פסוק. It's learned from the פסוק by עולה, olah,
היא העולה על המזבח כל הלילה. hee ha'olah al hamizbe'ach kol halaylah.
If it's put up, it stays up. So number one, maybe that's
unique to a מזבח, mizbe'ach maybe that nothing doesn't have to do
with מקדש, Mekadesh maybe that you know whatever even though the כלי
שרת kli shares are מקדשין mikaidashin maybe not in the same way.
Number one. Number two is is that as I said, by the
מזבח mizbe'ach, it's one thing to say it's up there it stays
up there you just move it to the fire. It's another thing
something's in a כלי שרת klei shares and you're going to say
now go זורק zorek the דם dam or something like that. So
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish wanted to know does the הלכה halacha apply
to this or not.
Okay, אמר ליה amar lei לכתחילה ליקרב קמיבעיא לי. l'chatchila l'hikarev kamiba'ei
lee. I want to know how far we go to the comparison
to מזבח. mizbe'ach, So he says הא נמי תנינא, ha nami tanina,
we also taught that שקיבלו פסולים וזרקו את דמו. shekiblu psulim v'zarku
es damo. One of the examples of where you can keep something
on the מזבח mizbe'ach. is that you misused the blood, okay. So
it's a very funny read רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to
read this because the simple read of this is, let's say a
פסול pasul person caught the blood, or or the key is the
word and or, or a פסול pasul person threw the blood. So
the blood was not good, okay, nevertheless, if you put the meat
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach it gets to stay on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
That was one of the הלכות halachos about something פסול pasul gets
to stay on the מזבח. mizbe'ach But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
going to read this that the ו vav is an and, a
פסול pasul person caught the blood and threw the blood. And that's
what made the meat פסול. pasul. So why did you have to
say a פסול pasul person did both? Why isn't it enough that
a פסול pasul person did one that makes the meat פסול? pasul?
מאי
לאו mai lav שקיבלו פסולים וזרקו פסולים? shekiblu psulim v'zarku psulim? And
therefore and now you know why you'd have to say he did
both rather than just one? Because if a פסול pasul person just
caught the blood, okay, the blood is פסול, pasul, but what? It's
in a כלי שרת! kli shares So you'd be allowed to throw
the blood. But only if the פסול pasul person went ahead and
threw it, the throwing invalidates it. But the actual catching in a
כלי שרת kli shares!
not invalid, you could throw it לכתחילה l'chatchila because it's in a
כלי שרת. kli shares That's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wanted to
read. Pretty radical idea that you could throw the blood לכתחילה l'chatchila
if it's in a כלי שרת kli shares. even if it's פסול.
pasul. So so the answer is, לא, lo, שקיבלו פסולים אי נמי
שזרקו פסולים shekiblu psulim ee nami shezarku psulim and that's the end
of the discussion. So this so you know it means or. So
we have this huge question, what does כלי שרת kli shares מקדש
mekadesh, mean? Does it mean it really allows you to ignore the
פסול pasul and now put it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach? okay, and
throw the blood? And we have no answer to it. We had
one text that was a bad proof, okay, and the גמרא Gemara
just leaves it unanswered, okay. מאי obviously to me you're hearing that
it's conceptually very strange to think, it's one thing to say it's
on the מזבח mizbe'ach, gets to stay there and you can even
move it to the fire. It's a very different thing to say
that something's in a כלי שרת kli shares לכתחילה l'chatchila you can
go ahead and offer it up, okay, and that that actually then
would seem to be, and not actually what the גמרא Gemara implies
is, right and this is different, if the meat is at the
top of the מזבח, mizbe'ach right, you get to go ahead and
keep it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but the קרבן korban was still
invalid, right, assuming that it was a פסול psul that was a
קרבן korban a whole פסול psul of the קרבן korban not just
of this piece of meat. Right here the implication is that if
the כלי שרת klei shares are מקדש, mekadesh, you could throw the
blood and the קרבן korban would be כשר. kasher. The only way
the קרבן korban became פסול pasul was because because the פסול pasul
person also threw it. Okay, so it's a pretty radical idea that
you could לכתחילה l'chatchila throw the פסול pasul blood and even that
the קרבן korban would be כשר kasher and the גמרא Gemara does
not resolve this. Yes.
Wasn't the water of the כיור kiyor like you know they have
to do this whole mechanism to immerse it in to
prevent it from becoming לינה.
It means you know the water was in a כלי שרת kli
shares so we still say there are problems.
That's an interesting question,
why didn't we say there too?
I don't know.
Yeah, I don't know. I mean certainly you're not supposed to לכתחילה
l'chatchila let it happen, but you're right, I mean the fact is
that the פשט pshat is that it would become לינה and become
invalid. Good question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so we had that huge question, what does it mean that
כלי שרת kli shares is מקדש, mekadesh, does it really let the
stuff be לכתחילה l'chatchila used and presumably even be good and make
the קרבן korban good? And we don't have an answer. New question.
Totally moving on. Okay, this is going to be a fun one.
אויר מזבח כמזבח דמי או לא. avir mizbe'ach k'mizbe'ach dami o lo.
We said the ramp, we said the כלי שרת, kli shares, what
about the air space of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, okay? Okay, so something
is, okay, you take your פסול נותר pasul notar meat or whatever
you have, your טמא tamei meat, okay, and it's not actually on
the מזבח mizbe'ach, itself, it's just, you know, it's just here hovering,
okay, it's hovering, okay, and let's say, I don't know, you could
imagine a case where somebody threw it up and the כהן kohen
here, we'll have that answer, here's your כהן, kohen,
threw it too far,
here's your כהן, kohen, okay, somebody threw it, he stuck out his
hand and he caught it, okay, okay, it never touched the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, it's just in his hand, okay, is he now allowed to
put it on the fire? Do we say מזבח מקדש mizbe'ach mekadesh,
or does he have to bring it off? Okay, so
אויר מזבח כמזבח דמי או לא? avir mizbe'ach kemizbe'ach dami o lo?
תשמע, tashma, כשם שהמזבח מקדש כך כבש מקדש. keshem shehamizbe'ach mekadesh kach
kevesh mekadesh. So now we're going to try to invert from the
ramp
הלכה. halacha. ואמרת אויר מזבח לאו כמזבח דמי, v'amarta avir mizbe'ach lav
kemizbe'ach dami, now if it's not like the altar, אויר כבש נמי
לאו ככבש דמי avir kevesh nami lav kekevesh dami then certainly the
air space of the ramp is not like the ramp.
היכי מסקליה מכבש למזבח הוי ירוד? heichi masklei michevesh lemizbe'ach havei yerud?
How would he bring it up from the ramp to the altar?
It's going to be like he brought it off, meaning not my
scenario, here was a little piece of meat that was left on
the ramp, okay, and it was טמא, tamei, let's say. Now the
הלכה halacha is okay, כבש מקדש kevesh mekadesh you're allowed to bring
it to the, to the fire. So what do you do? You
pick it up, right, and you walk and you put it in
the fire. Okay, as soon as you lift it up, you're in
the air space. So if the air space is not considered like
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's like it fell off the מזבח. mizbe'ach? The
הלכה halacha is if a פסול pasul thing falls off, you're not
allowed to bring it back up, right? So as soon as you
lifted it up, if the air space wasn't considered like the מזבח
mizbe'ach. itself, that's like it was taken off of the מזבח. mizbe'ach
If it's over here and it's not on the fire, you figure,
okay, kick it to the fire, something like that, it doesn't have
to go lift up, but here presumably you pick it up, so
why isn't that like it came off? It must be the air
space is like the מזבח mizbe'ach, itself. Mike, can you imagine what
it's going to answer? What would be a scenario that you can
get it to the fire without taking it off of the מזבח?
mizbe'ach, You rolled it up.
You roll it, you just drag it. So the גמרא Gemara says,
same way you could just kick the meat at the top of
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so the גמרא Gemara says, דנגדיה, denagdei, no, you
drag it, you never actually lift it off, it always remains in
contact with the
כבש. kevesh. והא אויר יש בין כבש למזבח? veha avir yesh bein
kevesh lemizbe'ach? Ah, but one minute, it's not total surface, there's a
tiny little gap between where the כבש kevesh ends and the מזבח
mizbe'ach, begins. So as soon as you are שלעפינג schlepping it and
you're going over that gap, so you're totally over the air space
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but this little piece of it that's riding
over the gap isn't actually directly in contact. It's one thing, you
know, which actually raises a good question, when you drag are you
allowed to drag it like this or assuming that we say the
air space doesn't count, you have to just push it the whole
way, the whole thing? So here it's assuming that if the air
space is a problem, if the air space is like off of
the מזבח, mizbe'ach the entire thing has to remain in contact. So
when it's going over the gap, part of it is not remaining
in contact. So the גמרא says,
so רובו לכבש ככבש רובו למזבח כמזבח, rubo l'kevesh k'kevesh rubo l'mizbe'ach
k'mizbe'ach,
that doesn't bother me, you go by where the majority of the
meat is. So if a little piece of it is not touching,
even if it all had to touch, wherever that piece isn't touching,
it's connected to where the majority of the piece of meat is.
So if a little isn't touching, it's like it's where the majority
is, and the majority is either on the כבש kevesh or it's
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach and therefore that doesn't bother me, it only
a tiny little piece, it goes by the majority. So the גמרא
says, תפשוט מהא דבעי רמי בר חמא, tifshot meha d'ba'ei rami bar
chama, let's conclude from this the question of רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama that רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked, יש חיבור
לעולין או לא? yesh chibur l'olin o lo? Does stuff that you're
putting on the מזבח, mizbe'ach? is it considered one unit or do
you look at each piece of it separately? Okay, you could ask
that question for example, right, let's assume that this הלכה halacha מזבח
מקדש, mizbe'ach mekadesh, let's assume
that some of it was on the כבש kevesh and some of
it was hovering off the כבש, kevesh, this טמא tamei piece of
meat, or like here, you know, some of it was like that.
Are you allowed to put the stuff that's not on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach is that considered like it's on the מזבח? mizbe'ach. Do we
look at it as one unit or not as one unit? So
that was יש חיבור לעולין yesh chibur l'olin or not? That was
his question, okay, so should we be able to conclude from here?
תפשוט, tifshot,
let's conclude that it is considered one unit, because if it's not,
then the piece that passes over the gap should be a problem.
So the גמרא says, תפשוט, tifshot, yes, fine, okay, according to the
way we're saying it, yes, that would lead to that conclusion that
we look at it as one unit. Okay, so you can't prove
from the case of the כבש kevesh that the air space is
considered like the מזבח. mizbe'ach, It could be the air space is
not the מזבח mizbe'ach and you just move it along the כבש
kevesh and you keep it all touching and connected. Okay, so מתקיף
לה, matkif lah, don't
you say like אין דרך עבודה בכך ein derech avoda b'kach and
you know that wouldn't have any problems with that?
We'll get to that soon enough. Okay, this is not an עבודה,
avoda, this is just getting it to the fire. That's not exactly
an עבודה. avodah. But we'll get to that soon enough. מתקיף ליה
רבה בר רב חנן. maskif lei Ravva bar Rav Chanan. רבה בר
רב חנן Ravva bar Rav Chanan asks, ואם אמרת אויר מזבח כמזבח
דמי, ve'im amarta avir mizbe'ach kemizbe'ach dami, one minute he says, I'm
going to ask in the other direction. The- if you say אויר
כמזבח avir kemizbe'ach is like the מזבח, mizbe'ach. עולת העוף דפסלה במחשבה
היכי משכחת
לה? olas ha'of de-paslah bemachshavah heichi mashkachat lah? Here you are, the
עולת העוף olas ha'of is done at the top of the מזבח,
mizbe'ach right? Here you are, you're at the top here, you're, you
know, with your whatever, you know, you're doing your thing, okay.
You're over the- you're by the אויר המזבח, avir hammizbe'ach, okay. You're
over the airspace, right? I mean, if you're let's say at the
walk around here or somewhere where you are, you're standing here, right,
with your bird in hand, okay. Now, a bird is worth two
in the bush. Exactly, two in the bush. Now, that's over the
airspace of the מזבח, mizbe'ach. right? I mean, the base comes here,
right, wherever you are, I mean, here you're standing on this thing,
you're in the airspace of the מזבח, mizbe'ach right? So you're doing
that and you're having a thought of חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, a
פיגול pigul thought. So here's fascinating because we never get out of
פיגול. pigul. The גמרא's assumption is a פיגול pigul thought can't be
worse than actually if you executed your thought. Okay? So you're thinking
about this and you're planning, I'm going to burn the meat- I'm
going to burn the meat two days from now. Okay, but let's
say you actually burn the meat two days from now. Right now
it's over the airspace of the מזבח, mizbe'ach מזבח mizbe'ach, is מקדש
mekaddesh and you'd be allowed to keep the meat there and burn
it two days from now. So since you'd be allowed to keep
the meat- I mean, if you were to keep- or let's put
it this way, were you to keep the meat there and burn
it two days from now, you would do nothing wrong because מזבח
mizbe'ach, would be מקדש, mekaddesh, you're over the airspace. So how could
your thought about doing that create a פסול psul if actually you
would be, you know, that would be okay to do if it
had been left in that space and you burned it two days
from now? So how could you have a פסול psul of a
thought of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano if you're over the airspace of
the
מזבח? mizbe'ach Alright, that's the question, yeah. So he says like this.
Are you convinced, Michael? You look convinced. Okay, he says עולת העוף
דפסלה במחשבה היכי משכחת לה. olas ha'of de-paslah bemachshavah heichi mashkachat lah.
הכא קלטה מזבח. haka kletah mizbe'ach. The מזבח's mizbe'ach. already absorbed it,
as it were. It's an absorption center. So מתקיף ליה רב שימי
בר אשי, maskif lei Rav Shimi bar Ashi, אלמא לא? alma lo?
Why is that such a problem? משכחת לה כגון דאמר הריני מולק
על מנת להורידה למחר ולהעלותה להקטרה. mashkachat lah kegon de'amar hareini molek
al menas lehoridah lemachar u-lehaalosah lehaktarah. I'm going to- I'm going to
sort of sever its neck, על מנת al menas להורידה למחר, lehoridah
lemachar, I'm going to, sure, I have a way that I can
turn it into נותר, okay, and that it won't be on the
מזבח. I'll bring it off of the מזבח, okay, and at,
you know, after daybreak, and then I'll put it back up. I
wouldn't be allowed to do that with the actual meat, so my
thought would make it נותר. So the גמרא says, הניחא לרבא דאמר
לינה מועלת בראשו של מזבח. hani'cha le-Ravva de'amar linah mo'eles berosho shel
mizbe'ach. Okay, for רבא, Ravva fine, you'll say you'll bring it off
of the מזבח after daybreak. It'll already be נותר. רבא says something
can become נותר after daybreak. אלא לרבה דאמר אין לינה מועלת בראשו
של מזבח ליכא למחשבתו. ella le-Rabbah de'amar ein linah mo'eles berosho shel
mizbe'ach leika lemachshavto. But according to רבה, even if you plan to
bring it off of- after daybreak, it didn't become לינה. So there's
an easy answer to that. Fine, I'll bring it down before daybreak.
לרבה נמי משכחת לה כגון דאמר הריני מולק על מנת להורידה קודם
עמוד השחר ולהעלותה לאחר עמוד השחר. le-Rabbah nami mashkachat lah kegon de'amar
hareini molek al menas lehoridah kodem amud hashachar u-lehaalosah le'achar amud hashachar.
That was an easy answer, right? So basically he says, yeah, it's
all very nice, you're right, if you left the bird here it
wouldn't become נותר and you'd be allowed to burn it. But that
doesn't mean you can't have a חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought. Your
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought is: I'll be מולק molek it, I'll
take it down, I'll wait for it to become נותר, and then
I'll put it back up. Okay, so just because right now you're
in the אויר המזבח avir hammizbe'ach doesn't mean you can't have a-
an act or a thought about a scenario that would actually- it
would be אסור assur to offer it up after חוץ לזמנו. chutz
lizmano.
So the גמרא says that the normal thought of פיגול, pigul, like,
I'm going to do this two days from now, doesn't count. It
has to be some weird thing where you're going to take it
down and put it back up?
In the case of the bird. That's the scenario. In the case
of the bird, if you just said I'm just going to, you
know, stay here till tomorrow and- I mean, one always wonders what's
your thought when you say I'm going to burn it tomorrow. Presumably
you're also planning you're going to go home or whatever you're going
to do in the- in the interim. But if you're- but maybe
you're not thinking about what you're doing with the meat in the
interim. So if your thought is just, I'm going to come back
up tomorrow, I'm going to leave the bird here and come back
up tomorrow and burn it, then the answer is, well, then why
is that- why is that a פיגול pigul thought? It'll be okay
to burn tomorrow if you leave it there. So the answer is
fine, but your point- point is you're going to take it down
and put it back up. So, okay. Alright, so anyway, so that
was an argument to say don't say it's אויר כמזבח. avir kemizbe'ach.
But the גמרא says that's not a proof. It's easy enough to
have a פיגול pigul thought even if you're in the airspace of
the מזבח. So the גמרא says אלא, ella, so the גמרא says,
להכא סמטי ביה. lehacha samti beih.
Fine,
but now that you introduced the idea of the bird, we can
actually use it to prove in the opposite direction. We can use
it to prove that the airspace of the מזבח is like the
מזבח. How are we going to prove that? דאויר מזבח כמזבח דמי.
de'avir mizbe'ach kemizbe'ach dami. דאי סלקא דעתך אויר מזבח לאו כמזבח דמי,
de'i salka daatach avir mizbe'ach lav kemizbe'ach dami, if it's not like
the altar, חטאת העוף פסולה היכי מזה מדמה הוי ליה ירוד. chatas
ha'of psulah heichi mazzeh middammah havei lei yerud.
So it says like this, so we have a הלכה, halachah, right,
that, remember, one of the things that... So we have a הלכה,
halacha, right, that remember one of the things that were said you're
allowed to do, remember there's a debate about what are the things
that are considered fit for the מזבח and there was a debate
whether it included the, what do you call it, whether it included
birds or not birds. Let's assume that the things that are fit
for the מזבח and get to stay that includes birds, okay? So
you've got now like a חטאת, chatat, okay? How are you going
to, a חטאת chatat bird, that's פסול, pasul, okay? And let's say,
right, you got this, let's say you're doing it, I don't know,
שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, right, because that's a חטאת, chatat, שלא לשמה
shelo lishma it's פסול. pasul. The הלכה halacha that מזבח
מקדש, mizbe'ach
mekadesh
let's go ahead and put it onto the מזבח, right? But now
the question is like this, how are you ever going to get
around
to,
so the הלכה halacha of מזבח מקדש says the stuff is already
on the מזבח, you're allowed to sprinkle the blood. That's presumably what
it says. Right? If, guys, you know what, it's already 8:30. So
let's end here because this is going to take too long to
explain and we will resume with this. I wanted to get to
the משנה, but we will pick up tomorrow at the very top
of this to explain how scenarios of the birds and whatever is
going to make it clear that the airspace of the מזבח counts
like the מזבח. Okay, we'll end here.